Ernest Cushing Richardson Collection of French and Italian Manuscripts
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ernest Cushing Richardson Collection of French and Italian Manuscripts 1179-1825
MSS76253
Richardson, Ernest Cushing, 1860-1939
2,000 items
14 containers
5.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Librarian and collector. Correspondence, legal notes, dictionaries of ecclesiastical and civil law, land records, genealogical material, financial records, pamphlets, printed material, and other manuscripts relating to mainly to France and Italy collected by Richardson. Subjects include law, medicine, and religion.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Richardson, Ernest Cushing, 1860-1939.
Subjects
Deeds--France.; Deeds--Italy.; Encyclopedias and dictionaries, French.; Genealogy--Italy.; Land tenure--France.; Land tenure--Italy.; Law--France--Dictionaries.; Law--France.; Law--Italy.; Medicine--France.
Places
France--History.; France--Religion.; Italy--History.; Italy--Religion.
Occupations
Collectors.; Librarians.
Provenance
The collection of Ernest Cushing Richardson, librarian and collector, was purchased by the Library of Congress in 1931.
Access and Restrictions
The Ermest Cushing Richardson Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1860, Feb. 9 Born, Woburn, Mass.
1879 1880 First assistant librarian, Amherst College, Amherst, Mass.
1880 A.B., Amherst College, Amherst, Mass.
1883 A.M., Amherst College, Amherst, Mass. Graduated, Hartford Theological Seminary, Hartford, Conn.
1884 1890 Librarian, Hartford Theological Seminary, Hartford Conn.
1885 1890 Associate professor of bibliography
1887 Ph.D., Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, Pa.
1890 1920 Librarian, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J.
1891 Married, Grace Duncan Ely
1896 Honorary A.M., Princeton University, Princeton, N.Y.
1900 1912 Member, New Jersey Public Library Commission
1904 1905 President, American Library Association
1915 1918 President, American Library Institute
1920 1923 Director, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J.
1923 1925 Honorary director emeritus and research professor of bibliography
1925 Consultant in bibliography and research, Library of Congress
1939, June 3 Died, Princeton, N.J.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of Ernest Cushing Richardson (1860-1939), a professor, bibliographer, theologian, and collector of rare material, spans the years 1179-1825 and consists of correspondence, legal notes, dictionaries of ecclesiastical and civil law, land records, genealogical material, financial records, pamphlets, printed material, and other manuscripts relating mainly to France and Italy. Subjects include law, medicine, and religion, mostly in French, with some Latin, Italian, and German.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Letters and manuscripts, in French, 1782-1819 (Box 1)
- Printed matter, in French, 1702-1815 (Box 1)
- Printed matter, pamphlets, in French, 1710-1825 (Box 1)
- “Coppie des acts qui sont dans le Trésor des chartes du Roy,” 1174-1231 (Box 2)
- Manuscripts and pamphlets, many relating to medicine and law, in French (Box 2)
- “Partages de meubles chancepie / Recepte à la succession de madame de la Gaulerie,” circa 1587-circa 1786 (Box 3)
- Legal notes and references, with miscellaneous documents, seventeen-nineteenth centuries, in French (Box 4)
- “Bail de Prevost 3e. Année d’ 8bre. 1764 / Bureau General / Entrées Journalières / Septième Volume” (Box 5)
- “Livre de depenses faite dans les voyages de M. Descharnières... Livres de la depense de Mlle. Sophie Charnières” (Box 6)
- Manuscript dictionary of ecclesiastical law[?], in French (Box 6)
- Manuscript dictionary of civil law[?], in French (Box 7)
  - A-R, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - S-V (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous manuscripts, in French (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous pamphlets, in French (Box 8)
- Papal Bulls, in Latin with seals [one of Clement XII, thirteen of Benedict XIV, and two of Clement XIII] (Box 9)
- Alonso of Sicily, 1443[?], regarding Church matters, in Latin (Box 10)
- Ferdinand II of Sicily, 1496, edict, in Latin (Box 10)
- Don Perafan de Ribera, duque de Alcala, 1564, transfer of lands in Calabria, in Latin (Box 10)
- Franciscus Bennius[?], Bishop of Ravello, 1605, appointment of Fabricius Confalonus, in Latin (Box 10)
- Laurentius Tramallus, 1639, deputization of Marco Antonio Oliva, in Latin (Box 10)
- Ferdinand III of the Holy Roman Empire, 1646, passport of Martin Schmidt and sons, in German (Box 10)
- Clement X, 1672, Papal Bull regarding founding of the Collegiate Church of Montecalvo, in Latin (Box 10)
- Duc de Lorraine, 1736, patent of nobility on behalf of Michael Jerome Kelly, in French (Box 10)
- Ferdinand IV of Sicily, 1772, edict, in Italian (Box 10)
- General Maggiore, 1772, patent, in Italian (Box 10)
- Gabriele Quattromani, 1841, enrollment in the Society of the Golden Cross, in Latin (Box 10)
- Genealogical notes and records of the Cerbarano family, 16th-18th centuries, one volume, in Italian (Box 11)
- Paul V, 1609, ecclesiastical document, in Latin with seal (Box 11)
- Tanner and Mitchell[?] to Walker, 1669, indenture (Box 11)
- Innocent XI, 1676, Capitularies, list, in Latin (Box 11)
- Jean Charles Masurier and family, eighteenth century, miscellaneous French documents (Box 11)
- Seventeen deeds, 1457-1594, in Latin (Box 12)
- Forty-two deeds, 1602-1789, in Latin, Italian and French (Box 13)
- “Tome I des Contrats d'acquêts, faits en la mouvance des fiefs des Douves et de Bossé.. .,” fifteenth-eighteenth centuries, in French (Box 14)
- “Titres de propriété.. .,” regarding families Barrault, Chollet, and others, fifteenth-eighteenth centuries, in French (Box 14)